Where is the array information stored?
What's the objecttype of an interface?
Can I have full control over the classloader?

Where is the array information stored?

The Type class stores array information in it. If the array is multidimensional, the dimension depth can be accessed.

What's the object type of an interface?

The JavaClass method is used to represent both classes and interfaces. The isInterface() method allows you to distinguish between the two.

When using a class, the getSuperClass() return which class is extended. If this has not been defined in the input source code, java.lang.Object is returned. When using an interface, this method ALWAYS returns null.

When using a class, the getImplements() returns an array of the interfaces implemented by the class. If none are implemented, an empty array is returned. When using an interface, this returns an array of interfaces the current interface EXTENDS.

Can I have full control over the classloader?

I some cases QDox is used to generate classes for another project with it's own dependencies. This could result in class-collission. By default the JavadocBuilder will contain the classloader(s) of the current project, but by defining your own classLibrary you can have the required control.

    /* new ClassLibrary() will give you an empty classLoader
     * Big chance you want at least the system classloader.
     */	
    ClassLibrary classLibrary = new ClassLibrary( ClassLoader.getSystemClassLoader() );
    JavaDocBuilder builder = new JavaDocBuilder(classLibrary);
    
      

Migrating to QDox 2.0

Farewell JavaDocBuilder, hello JavaProjectBuilder

Farewell OrderedMap, hello LinkedHashMap

Before JDK1.3 there was no implementation available which could hold the order in which entries were added to a Map. With JDK1.4 the LinkedHashMap was introduced. We've decided to make use of this class which also means projects using QDox need at least JDK1.4. If you want QDox to parse code with an older JDK version, you'll have to configure the ClassLoaderLibrary feeding it with the required classloaders.

Farewell JavaClass, hello JavaClass

Looks like nothing has changed, but we've decided to change all models to interfaces and give them a default implementation. This way we can hide all methods which the ModelBuilder needs to build the model and you'll only see those methods which are interesting for you. This also means that the default implementations looks much more like plain old Java Objects, its binding logic has been moved to the ModelBuilder.

Farewell AbstractQDoxTask for Ant

We've decided to remove this Abstract AntTask. It doesn't belong in the core of QDox, but it's an prepared Ant Task to use QDox. Although we'd defined this dependency as optional, it kind of spoiled the pom.xml.

Farewell APITestCase for JUnit3

Summary

Use the JavaProjectBuilder instead of the JavaDocBuilder
QDox requires at least JDK1.4

After the source code has been parsed, the content of the files can be navigated using a simple to use and intuitive object model.

JavaSource

Represents a complete .java file. This contains a collection of classes.

Example Input

    package com.blah.foo;
    
    import java.awt.*;
    import java.util.List;
    
    public class Class1 {
      ...
    }
    
    class Class2 {
    }
    
    interface Interface1 {
    }
            

Example Code

    JavaProjectBuilder builder = new JavaProjectBuilder();
    JavaSource src = builder.addSource(myReader);
    
    JavaPackage pkg      = src.getPackage(); 
    List<String> imports     = src.getImports(); // {"java.awt.*",
                                         //  "java.util.List"}
    
    JavaClass class1     = src.getClasses().get(0);
    JavaClass class2     = src.getClasses().get(1);
    JavaClass interface1 = src.getClasses().get(2);
            

JavaPackage

Represents the package of the class.

Example input

    package com.blah.foo;
    
    public class BarClass  {
    ...
    }
  

Example Code

    JavaProjectBuilder builder = new JavaProjectBuilder();
    JavaSource src = builder.addSource(myReader);
    
    JavaPackage pkg      = src.getPackage();
    
    Collection<JavaClass> classes  = pkg.getClasses(); // BarClass
    String name          = pkg.getName(); // "com.blah.foo"
    String toString      = pkg.toString(); // "package com.blah.foo" conform javaAPI
    JavaPackage parent   = pkg.getParentPackage(); //
  

JavaClass

Represents a class or interface. This contains doclet tags, fields and methods. Information about the class definition is available, such as which classes are extended, which interfaces implemented and modifiers.

Example Input

    package com.blah.foo;
    
    import java.io.*;
    import com.custom.*;
    import com.base.SubClass;
    
    /**
     * @author Joe
     */
    public abstract class MyClass extends SubClass
                implements Serializable, CustomInterface  {
    
      private String name;
      public void doStuff() { ... }
      private int getNumber() { ... }
    
    }
  

Example Code

    JavaProjectBuilder builder = new JavaProjectBuilder();
    builder.addSource(myReader);
    
    JavaClass cls = builder.getClassByName("com.blah.foo.MyClass");
    
    String pkg      = cls.getPackage();            // "com.blah.foo"
    String name     = cls.getName();               // "MyClass"
    String fullName = cls.getCanonicalName(); // "com.blah.foo.MyClass";
    String canonicalName = cls.getFullyQualifiedName(); // "com.blah.foo.MyClass";
    boolean isInterface = cls.isInterface();       // false
    
    boolean isPublic   = cls.isPublic();   // true
    boolean isAbstract = cls.isAbstract(); // true
    boolean isFinal    = cls.isFinal();    // false
    
    JavaType superClass = cls.getSuperClass(); // "com.base.SubClass";
    List<JavaType> imps     = cls.getImplements(); // {"java.io.Serializable",
                                           //  "com.custom.CustomInterface"}
    
    String author = cls.getTagsByName("author").getValue(); // "joe"
    
    JavaField nameField = cls.getFields()[0];
    JavaMethod doStuff = cls.getMethods()[0];
    JavaMethod getNumber = cls.getMethods()[1];
    
    JavaSource javaSource = cls.getParentSource();
  

JavaField

Represents a field in a class. This has doclet tags, a name and a type.

Example Input

    import java.util.Date;
    
    public class MyClass  {
    
      /**
       * @magic
       */
      private String email;
    
      public static Date[][] dates;
    
    }
            

Example Code

    JavaField e = cls.getFields()[0];
    
    JavaType eType     = e.getType(); // "java.lang.String";
    String eName   = e.getName(); // "email";
    DocletTag eTag = e.getTagsByName("magic"); // @magic
    boolean eArray = e.getType().isArray(); // false;
    
    JavaField d = cls.getFields()[1];
    
    JavaType dType     = d.getType(); // "java.util.Date";
    String dName   = d.getName(); // "dates";
    DocletTag dTag = d.getTagsByName("magic"); // null
    boolean dArray = d.getType().isArray(); // true;
    int dDimensions= d.getType().getDimensions(); // 2;
    boolean dStatic= d.isStatic(); // true;
    
    JavaClass javaClass = d.getParentClass();
            

JavaMethod

Represents a method in a class. This has doclet tags, a name, return type, parameters and exceptions.

Example Input

    import java.util.Date;
    import java.io.*;
    
    public class MyClass  {
    
      /**
       * @returns Lots of dates
       */
      public static Date[] doStuff(int number,
                                   String stuff)
                throws RuntimeException, IOException {
        ...
      }
    
    }
  

Example Code

    JavaMethod m = cls.getMethods()[0];
    
    String mName = m.getName(); // "doStuff";
    JavaType mReturns = m.getReturns(); // "java.util.Date";
    boolean mArray = m.getReturns().isArray(); // true
    boolean mStatic = m.isStatic(); // true
    boolean mPublic = m.isPublic(); // true
    
    String doc = m.getTagByName("returns").getValue();
      // "Lots of dates"
    
    List<JavaType> exceptions = m.getExceptions();
      // {"java.lang.RuntimeException", "java.io.IOException"}
    
    JavaParameter numberParam = m.getParameters()[0];
    JavaParameter stuffParam = m.getParameters()[1];
    
    JavaClass javaClass = m.getParentClass();
  

JavaParameter

Represents a parameter passed to a method. This has a name and a type.

Example Input

    public class MyClass  {
    
      public void stuff(int n, Object[] objects) {
        ...
      }
    
    }
  

Example Code

    JavaMethod m = cls.getMethods()[0];
    
    JavaParameter n = m.getParameters()[0];
    String nName = n.getName(); // "n"
    JavaType nType   = n.getType(); // "int";
    
    JavaParameter o = m.getParameters()[1];
    String oName   = o.getName(); // "objects"
    JavaType oType     = o.getType(); // "java.lang.Object";
    boolean oArray = o.getType().isArray(); // true
    
    JavaMethod javaMethod = o.getParentMethod();
  

JavaType

Represents a specific instance of a class used by another class (such as return value, superclass, etc). The value represents the name of the class. Array dimensions are also available. Since 1.8 it's also possible to get the generic value of the Type

Example Input

    
  
    import java.util.*;
    
    public class MyClass  {
    
      public void stuff(int n, Object[] objects,
    	                  Date[][] dates, List stringList) {
        ...
      }
    
    }
    
  

Example Code

    JavaMethod m = cls.getMethods()[0];
    
    JavaType returns = m.getReturns();
    returns.getValue(); // "void"
    returns.isArray(); // false
    returns.getDimensions(); // 0
    
    JavaType n = m.getParameters()[0].getType();
    n.getValue(); // "int"
    n.isArray(); // false
    n.getDimensions(); // 0
    
    JavaType objects = m.getParameters()[1].getType();
    objects.getValue(); // "java.lang.Object"
    objects.isArray(); // true
    objects.getDimensions(); // 1
    
    JavaType dates = m.getParameters()[2].getType();
    dates.getValue(); // "java.util.Date"
    dates.isArray(); // true
    dates.getDimensions(); // 2
    
    JavaType stringList = m.getParameters()[3].getType();
    stringList.getValue(); // "java.util.List"
    stringList.getGenericValue(); // "java.util.List"
    stringList.isArray(); // false
    stringList.getDimensions(); // 0
          

DocletTag

Represents a JavaDoc tag. Each tag has a name and a value. Optionally, the value can be broken up into tokens accessed by index or name.

The JavaClass, JavaField and JavaMethod classes all support comments and DocletTags

The returned DocletTag carries the name, value and methods for breaking up the value into specific parameters.

Example Input

    /**
     * This method does nothing at all.
     *
     * @returns A boolean of whether we care or not.
     * @param email Someone's email address.
     * @param dob Date of birth.
     *
     * @permission administrator full-access
     * @webservice publish=true name=myservice type=rpc
     */
    boolean doWeCare(String email, Date dob);
            

Example Code

    JavaMethod mth = cls.getMethods()[0];
    
    // Access the JavaDoc comment
    String comment = mth.getComment();
      // "This method does nothing at all."
    
    // Access a single doclet tag
    DocletTag returns = mth.getTagByName("returns");
    returns.getName(); // "returns";
    returns.getValue(); // "A boolean of whether we care or not."
    
    // Access multiple doclet tags with the same name
    DocletTag[] params = mth.getTagsByName("param");
    params[0].getValue(); // "Someone's email address."
    params[1].getValue(); // "Date of birth."
    
    // Access specific parameters of a doclet tag by index
    DocletTag permission = mth.getTagByName("permission");
    permission.getParameter[0]; // "administrator"
    permission.getParameter[1]; // "full-access"
    
    // Access specific parameters of a doclet tag by name
    DocletTag webservice = mth.getTagByName("webservice");
    webservice.getNamedParameter("type"); // "rpc"
    webservice.getNamedParameter("name"); // "myservice"
           

Upgrading to 1.10.1 or above

This section describes what needs to be done when upgrading to QDox 1.10.1.

Things that might break your code

In some cases the Type.toString() was inconsequent (QDOX-182) so we had to change the implementation. If you use this in combination with innerClasses you should use Type.getFullyQualifiedName() to get the same result.

Upgrading to 1.10 or above

This section describes what needs to be done when upgrading to QDox 1.10.

Things that might break your code

The toString()-method in most of the JavaObjects under com.thoughtworks.qdox.models used to return the corresponding codeblock. This method has been renamed to getCodeBlock(). The toString() will follow the Java API Specs as described for each equivalent object under the java.lang-package. Some methods require extra attention, because there's not an exact match. Watch out for differences between Type and JavaClass.

Java API | QDOX
((java.lang.Method) aMethod).getReturnsType().toString() | ((com.thoughtworks.qdox.model.JavaMethod) aMethod).getReturns().toString()

com.thoughtworks.qdox.model.Type.getValue() will return the typeName for usage in the code. The new method com.thoughtworks.qdox.model.Type.getFullQualifiedName() will return the FQN as defined by the java specs. Normally they would return the same value, but pay attention when using inner classes.

Upgrading to 1.9 or above

This section describes what needs to be done when upgrading to QDox 1.9.

Things that might break your code

In both JavaClass and JavaSource the getPackage() returns an object of type JavaPackage instead of a String. To get the same result as before use getPackage().getName() .

Upgrading to 1.6 or above

This section describes what needs to be done when upgrading to QDox 1.6. For an extensive list of changes (most of them backwards compatible), please see the Changes Report.

Things that might break your code

In JavaClass the getInnerClasses() method has been renamed to getNestedClasses(). The old name remains as a (deprecated) synonym.

With support for generic types, we've introduced a bug affecting the use of "<" and ">" in initialisers (see QDOX-71).

Upgrading to 1.5

This section describes what needs to be done when upgrading to QDox 1.5. For an extensive list of changes (most of them backwards compatible), please see the Changes Report.

Things that might break your code

The DocletTag interface no longer contains a setContext() method. That information is now provided via DocletTagFactory, where createDocletTag() now requires an additional "context" parameter.

The parser now passes tag-data to Builders using a new TagDef structure.

Upgrading to 1.3

This section describes what needs to be done when upgrading to QDox 1.3. For an extensive list of changes (most of them backwards compatible), please see the Changes Report.

Things that might break your code

(Thanks to Peter Donald for contributing this list).

DocletTag is now an interface and needs to be replaced with DefaultDocletTag
JavaClass has changed so that there is no setParent but instead you need to pass the parent into the constructor.
JavaClassParent now has to additional methods that need to be implemented if you implement it: getClassLibrary() and resolveType(java.lang.String).

Entry Point

JavaProjectBuilder is the entry point to QDox. It is responsible for parsing source code, resolving imports and storing the data.

To create it, all you need to do is call the default constructor.

JavaProjectBuilder builder = new JavaProjectBuilder();

Reading Source Files

Java source code can then be added to the JavaProjectBuilder. Source can either be read one file at a time (using a java.io.Reader) or an entire source tree can be added recursively.

// Reading a single source file.
builder.addSource(new FileReader("MyFile.java"));

// Reading from another kind of input stream.
builder.addSource(new StringReader("package test; public class Hello {}"));

// Adding all .java files in a source tree (recursively).
builder.addSourceTree(new File("mysrcdir"));

Resolving Class Names

In order to resolve classes that have been imported using a wildcard (e.g. import java.util.*;), the ClassLibrary must be aware of other classes used in the project.

ClassLibrary has 4 ways to resolve classes:

By looking at other sources that have been added.
By searching through the supplied sourceFolders
By looking in the current classpath (including the standard JRE classes).
By looking at additional ClassLoaders specified at runtime.

All sources and sourcetrees added to the JavaProjectBuilder will be parsed. This is often much more than required. To increase efficiency use the ClassLibrary to add sourcefolders. Consider these files as lazy parsed sources.

The current classpath is automatically set by JavaProjectBuilder. In most cases this shall be sufficient, however in some situations you may want resolve the full classes in external libraries.

// Get the ClassLibrary
JavaProjectBuilder builder = new JavaProjectBuilder();

// Add a sourcefolder;
builder.addSourceFolder( new File( "src/main/java" ) );
builder.addSourceFolder( new File( "target/generated-sources/foobar" ) );

// Add a custom ClassLoader
builder.addClassLoader( myCustomClassLoader );

// Ant example : add the <classpath> element's contents
builder.addClassLoader( new AntClassLoader( getProject(), classpath ) );

It is important that additional ClassLoaders are added before any source files are parsed.

Navigating The Model

Now the files have been parsed, move on to navigating the model.

Project | Description | How QDox is Used
AspectWerkz | AspectWerkz is an Aspect Oriented Programming (AOP) toolkit for Java that modifies byte-code to weave in interceptors and mixins. | Attributes can be used to associate interceptors and mixins with a specific class.
Avalon Phoenix | Phoenix was a micro-kernel designed and implemented on top of the Avalon framework. It provided a number of facilities to manage the environment of Server Applications. Apache cancelled the Avalon project 2004 | 'MetaGenerate' is part of the Phoenix toolset and picks up @phoenix prefixed JavaDoc tags to make XML manifests for the components that will be laced together in more XML to make a complete server application.
Cocoon | Apache Cocoon is an XML publishing framework that raises the usage of XML and XSLT technologies for server applications to a new level. Designed for performance and scalability around pipelined SAX processing, Cocoon offers a flexible environment based on a separation of concerns between content, logic, and style. | The QDox Block reads in Java source files and fires out SAX events enabling processing by standard XML tools (such as XSLT).
Commons Attributes | Jakarta Commons Attributes provides an API to runtime metadata attributes. Attributes are specified as doclet tags and then compiled into the classpath where they can be accessed at runtime (without requiring the source). The aim is to provide a framework similar to .NET attributes. | QDox is used to extract the JavaDoc tags from the source files.
GWT-maven-plugin | The gwt-maven-plugin provides support for GWT projects, including running the GWT developer tools (the compiler, shell and i18n generation) and performing support operations to help developers make GWT fit more closely in with their standard JEE web application development (debugging, managing the embedded server, running noserver, merging web.xml, generating I18N interfaces, generating Async GWT-RPC interfaces, and more) and environment (Eclipse IDE). | QDox is used to generate the Async GWT-RPC interfaces based on their Service-classes.
Ivory | Ivory provides easy integration between your exiting Java classes, Avalon services, and Axis. It allows easy deployment of soap services with none of the WSDD configuration that Axis normally mandates. | Attributes are used to provide additional hints to Ivory about Java classes that cannot be determined via reflection.
maven-javadoc-plugin | The Javadoc Plugin uses the Javadoc tool to generate javadocs for the specified project. | When developers write code, they could forget to create (or update) the Javadoc comments. The <fix> and <test-fix> goals are interactive goals to fix the actual Javadoc comments.
Maven 2 | Maven is a software project management and comprehension tool. | QDox is used for extraction of Javadoc tags from source files to generate plugin descriptors
Mock Maker | Mock Maker is a tool for automatically generating mock objects from custom classes to aid in testing the untestable. This supports the practises of Test Driven Development and eXtreme Programming. | Mock Maker scans the source repository for any class/interface marked with the @mock JavaDoc tag and automatically creates the Mock Object for this that matches the class definition.
Nanning | Nanning is an Aspect Oriented Programming (AOP) toolkit for Java that does not require a custom compiler. It uses dynamic proxies to weave in interceptors and mixins at runtime. | QDox is used to allow aspects to be applied to classes by specifiying meta-data in doclet tags.
Paranamer | Paranamer a mechamism for accessing the parameter names of methods of Java classes compiled into jars | QDox is used to parse the source and generate the parameter names list.
Spring ME | A version of Spring that not only has a very small runtime footprint (none), but also is capable of running on small handheld devices, since it does not rely on reflection. |
vDoclet | vDoclet is a framework for code-generation using Velocity templates, based on annotated Java source-code. | vDoclet uses QDox to produce input-data for it's templates.
Voruta | Voruta is a data access framework for embedding SQL statements in Java methods using custom JavaDoc tags and dynamic code generation at runtime. | QDox is used to parse metadata and CGLib to generate implementation at runtime.
XDoclet2 | XDoclet2 is a framework for code-generation using Velocity or Jelly templates, based on annotated Java source-code. It is a rewrite of XDoclet. | XDoclet2 uses QDox to produce input-data for it's templates, as well as QDox' APITestCase to validate the generated sources.